The Grenfell Press Archive
Rare Book and Special Collections Division, Library of Congress
The Grenfell Press Archive 1980-1996 1982-1986
RB010002
Library of Congress. Rare Book and Special Collections Division
31 containers Linear feet of shelf space occupied: 30 feet Approximate number of items: 10,000
Rare Book and Special Collections Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The collection is divided into five categories: Correspondence and Typescripts, Grenfell Press Publications, Miscellaneous Publications, and Oversize materials.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Cole, Peter, 1957- --Correspondence.; Creeley, Robert, 1926-2005--Correspondence.; Davenport, Guy--Correspondence.; Dowell, Coleman--Correspondence.; Duncan, Robert Edward, 1919-1988--Correspondence.; Gass, William H., 1924- --Correspondence.; Hawkes, John, 1925-1998--Correspondence.; Howe, Susan, 1937- --Correspondence.; Laughlin, James, 1914-1997--Correspondence.; Lauterbach, Ann, 1942- --Correspondence.; Mathews, Harry, 1930- --Correspondence.; Miller, Leslie, 1957- --Correspondence.; Morrow, Bradford, 1951- --Correspondence.; Sorrentino, Gilbert--Correspondence.
Organizations
Grenfell Press Archive (Library of Congress) DLC; Grenfell Press.; Grenfell Press.
Subjects
Book design--United States--History--20th century--Sources.; Bookbinding--Specimens.; Paper--Specimens.
Places
New York (N.Y.)--Imprints.
Form/Genre
Book designers' mock-ups (Publishing); Broadsides.; Ephemera.; Page proofs (Printing); Trial proofs.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The Grenfell Press Archive was purchased by the Library of Congress in 1993. This original purchase includes correspondence and production materials associated with the operation of the Grenfell Press from its beginning in 1979 through 1992. Also included are several published items that were lacking from the Rare Book Collection's almost complete holdings of Grenfell Press titles; these items have been cataloged separately and housed with the Grenfell Press Collection. The Grenfell Press Archive has been arranged chronologically in order that, as works continue to be published, additional installments may be acquired and the archive expanded.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the Grenfell Press materials are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Rare Book and Special Collections Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
Leslie Miller began her press in 1979 with the broadside Typefaces and the next year produced her first book with the same title. Over the next decade she has since collaborated with the authors Joyce Carol Oates, Guy Davenport, James Laughlin, Ann Lauterbach, John Hawkes, Gilbert Sorrentino, William S. Burroughs, William Gass, Harry Mathews, Bradford Morrow, and the artists Trevor Winkfield, Francesco Clemente, James Nares, Ellen Phelan, Joel Shapiro, and others. Initially the press produced fine press books, but in recent years it has moved successfully into the livre d'artiste category.
No aspect of bookmaking escapes Miller's intense interest, which is most unusual in a world where printmakers often care little about typography, typographers look upon binding as a distracting afterthought, and binders view all of it merely as a medium for their own form of expression. These fractured attitudes result in books that are interesting in particulars but defective as wholes. Miller has managed to transcend the limitations any one of these crafts might have imposed upon her vision, creating books that are thoroughly imaginative. The ideal of the press is to create a book that is a balanced and unified statement in which all of its integral parts illuminate one another.
- Larry Sullivan, Chief Rare Book and Special Collections Division
The Grenfell Press Archive, which chronicles the book production, publicity, and business transactions associated with the Grenfell Press, has been arranged broadly into three categories: correspondence and typescripts, material relating to the production of individual works published by the Grenfell Press, and material relating to miscellaneous publications designed (but not published) by the press. The section comprising correspondence and typescripts relates to general business matters of the press; correspondence relating specifically to the production of an individual work is grouped with the production materials for that work. These production materials have been arranged in chronological order by publication date of the item to which they relate and subarranged by type; for example, correspondence, followed by typescripts and paste-ups, material relating to illustration and binding, etc. The original 1993 purchase also includes several published items that were lacking from the Rare Book Collection's almost complete holdings of Grenfell Press titles; these items have been cataloged separately (a source note has been added to the cataloging record to identify them) and housed with the Grenfell Press Collection. Also, in order to connect the material in the archive generally to the resulting publications housed in the Grenfell Press Collection, the record number for each publication is noted in parentheses in this finding aid. An index of names (authors and artists) and titles of publications has also been provided, but it should be noted that the section comprising correspondence and typescripts has not been indexed.
Correspondence and Typescripts (1981-1989) General business correspondence (1980-1994), miscellaneous typescripts and material relating to small projects (e.g., stationery, bookplates, etc.)
The Grenfell Press Publications (1980-1994) Correspondence associated with the production of a particular publication; production materials, including typescripts, proofs, paste-ups, binder's dummies, etc.; prospectuses and material relating to publicity.
The Miscellaneous Publications (1981-1991) Publications designed by the Grenfell Press, including work for New Directions, Callaway Editions, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, Targ Editions, Conjunctions Magazine, etc.
Pamphlets ( series contains Pamphlets, short monographs, off prints, and photocopies, primarily of published materials, in English and west European languages. Many published by anarchist organizations, many with inscriptions. Arranged alphabetically by author/title.
The Oversize (1983-1992) Oversize material organized and described according to the series, folders, and boxes from which the items were removed.
Arrangement of the Records
This collection is arranged in 4 series:
Correspondence and Typescripts, 1-6
Grenfell Press Publications, 7-19
Miscellaneous Publications, 20-23
Oversize, 24-54
http://lccn.loc.gov/94242533
Container List
- Correspondence and Typescripts 1981-1989 (Box 1-6)
  Correspondence and typescripts of the Grenfell Press.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Abish, Walter and Cecil, 3 items. (Box 1)
  - Typescript for Walter Abish, The Coming Ice Age, and one letter.
  - Ablenas, Rob - Balakian, Nona, 9 items.
  - Baldwin, Sarah - Berssenbrugge, Mei-Mei, 10 items.
  - Bertram Rota Ltd., Booksellers, 7 items; also 2 catalogs.
  - Beyond Baroque Bookstore, 1 item.
  - Blackstamps, also invoice, notes, material relating to illustrations., 2 items
  - Block, David - Borneman, Bill, 5 items.
  - Brainard, Joe, 2 items
  - Brawer, Jerome - Broomfield, Michael, 11 items
  - Brown, John L. - Burton, David K., 9 items.
  - Busch, Frederick; also samples of stationery, 10 items
  - Cadmus Editions; also business card, logo, notes, 11 items
  - Califa Books; also invoices, one catalog., 4 items
  - Campbell, Lee - Cleveland Institute of Art, 6 items.
  - Cobb, Hope - Cole, Morrill, 10 items.
  - Cooney, Seamus - Cooper, Jeffrey, 7 items.
  - Corso, Gregory. Proposals for printing (Meriden-Stinehour Press), notes, receipt.
  - Corso, Gregory. Typescript for Gregory Corso, The Day After Humankind. (See also: Oversize: Folders)., (2 copies).
  - Corso, Gregory. Typescript for Rene Richard, Painting in the Fog.
  - Crane, Joan - Day, Jean, 5 items.
  - D'Offay, Anthony. Correspondence
    - Leslie Miller to Anthony d'Offay, 1989, 1 item
    - Fern Malouin (Meredian Printing), 1981 also, photocopy relating to exhibition (Fawbush Gallery), material relating to d'Offay stationery, (See Oversize)., 1 item.
  - Dogear Wryde Paper Pastime, 2 items.
  - Duce, Luciana - Fisher, Linda, 13 items. (Box 2)
  - Fox, George K. - Gold, Joseph, 14 items.
  - Goldschmid, Johanna - Gottlieb, Leonard, 9 items.
  - Granary Books; also one catalog., 12 items
  - Grauerholz, James - Hagedorn, Jessica, 28 items.
  - Hawkes, John, 10 items; Rosmarie (Burning Deck), 1985, 2 items; leather covered boards.
  - Heisler, Elaine - Hollander, Susan, 6 items.
  - Horowitz, Glenn - Howes, Barbara, 2 items.
  - Irby, Ken; also typescript and printed poem., 2 items.
  - Jackson, Laura Riding, Keynes, Quentin, 11 items.
  - Knight, Arthur - Krisilas, John G., 6 items.
  - Kuhlmann, Edward - Leach, David, 6 items.
  - Lee C. Milazzo, Fine Books, 7 items.
  - Lepper, Gary M. - Marden, Brice, 7 items.
  - McComish, Philip - Monahan, P. Matthew, 8 items.
  - Morrow, Bradford. (Box 3)
  - Odlin, Reno W., 5 items.
  - Ohannessian, Griselda - Paul, S., 8 items.
  - Penny Frank Dance Works - Pharos Books, 9 items.
  - Phillips, Matt. Material relating to Moroccan Scenes, (1983?).
  - Phillpot, Clive - Pomerantz, Marsha, 2 items.
  - Preiss, Byron., 14 items. (Box 4)
  - Quartermain, Peter, 8 items.
  - Quesoda, Carmen - Renzi, Ralph, 3 items.
  - Rippon, Laurie and Peter.
  - Rodney, Janet - Roth, David, 8 items.
  - Rummonds, Gabriel - Sharrard, Robert, 14 items.
  - Shirley, Betsy, 24 items.
  - Shoemaker, Jack - Strider, Charles, 11 items. (Box 5)
  - Tarn, Nathaniel.
  - Targ, William - Vanacore, Frederick, 14 items.
  - Vincent Fitz Gerald and Company - Yett, Daniel, 16 items.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 17 items. (Box 6)
  - Museums, Libraries, and other organizations, 21 items.
  - University Correspondence, 47 items.
  - Mailing list requests.
  - Mailing/Correspondence lists.
  - Greeting Cards, announcements, etc.
  - Miscellaneous postcards, 20 items.
  - Miscellaneous catalogues, guides, etc.
  - Ephemera, 3 items.
  - Posters, 2 items.
- Grenfell Press Publications 1980-1994 (Box 7-19)
  Correspondence associated with the production of a particular publication; production materials, including typescripts, proofs, paste-ups, binder's dummies, etc.; prospectuses and material relating to publicity.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Typefaces, etc., (82-466167) 1980. (Box 7)
    - Prospectuses:
  - Brooke, Susan. Stately Progress. (81-179619)
    - Prospectuses
  - Dowell, Coleman. The Silver Swanne, (85-229951) See also: Oversize: Broadside 1983.
    - Correspondence, Coleman Dowell; envelope from Claudia Cohen, 1982-83>, 8 items.
    - Typescripts, incl. issue of AMBIT
    - Material relating to initial, plus paper samples
    - Proofs, title-pages and preliminaries
    - Annotated proofs (layout), paper samples
    - Material relating to illustration
    - Paste-ups
    - Paper samples
    - Paper samples, receipts
    - Unbound sheets (Box 8)
    - Printed book (binder's dummy)
    - Material relating to prospectus, advertising, incl. 1 letter from Thorn Gunn
  - Davenport, Guy. The Bowmen of Shu, 1983. Illustration by Guy Davenport, Henri Gaudier-Brzeska. (85-226899) See also: Oversize: Broadsides.
    - Correspondence, Guy Davenport, plus illustrations for Christmas card 1981-88, (69 items)
    - Annotated typescript
    - Material relating to illustrations Departure of the Argonaut
    - Proofs, text and illustrations
    - Material relating to page layout 11-13. Paste-ups, incl. photocopy
    - Paper samples, letter from Leslie Miller, concerning printing 1983
    - Material relating to prospectus
  - Sobin, Gustav. Ten Sham Haikus. (95-119542) See also: Oversize: Broadsides1983. (Box 9)
    - Manuscript books, handmade by Sobin, sewn in Provencal paper
    - Paste-ups and notes on production Broadsides
    - Paste-ups and notes on production
    - Unbound sheets
  - Laughlin, James. Lines for Ezra Pound and William Carlos Williams, (95-119457) 1983
    - Correspondence, James Laughlin, 1983-1990 Ann (Mrs. James Laughlin), 1984
    - Typescript, incl. 1 letter from James Laughlin, and invoice, 1983.
    - Material relating to drawing by Guy Davenport and sincerity ideogram, incl. 1 letter, Griselde?, dated without year
    - Paste-up, mock-up, both in paper wrappers
    - Galleys, incl. 1 letter from James Laughlin, 1983
    - Paper samples
  - Lauterbach, Ann. Sacred Weather. Illustration by Louisa Chase. (85-229956) 1984. See also: Oversize Broadsides
    - Correspondence, Ann Lauterbach, 1983-87 Lee Milazzo, undated Leslie Miller to Louisa, 1984
    - Typescript
    - Proofs, notes on production
    - Type specimens
    - Material relating to illustration
    - Paste-up
    - Dummy binding
    - Proof loose in paper boards
    - Promotional material
  - Hawkes, John. Innocence in Extremis. Illustration by T.L. Solein. (86-130293). See also: Oversize: Broadsides, Small Broadsides, 1985 (Box 10)
    - Correspondence, Leslie Miller to T.L. Solein, 1984-85; Leslie Miller to T.L. Solein / verso: to J. Hawkes, undated; Rosmarie Waldrop (Burning Deck), 1985 Jack [John] Hawkes, 1985; clipping, invoice
    - Typescripts
    - Proofs
    - Original artwork by T.L. Solein
    - Unbound sheets
    - Paste-up
    - Leather samples
  - Sorrentino, Gilbert. A Beehive Arranged on Humane Principles, Illustration by David Storey. (86-189460) See also: Oversize: Broadsides, Small Broadsides 1985. (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, Gilbert Sorrentino, 1983, (19 items)
    - Typescript
    - Notes on production, type specimens, promotional material
    - Proofs, materials relating to layout
    - Paste-up
    - Unbound sheets
  - Gass, William. Culp, 1985. Illustration by Malcolm Morley. (85-174842) See also: Oversize: Broadsides, Small Broadsides, (19 items)
    - Correspondence, William Gass, War 1983-85
    - Photocopy of paste-up
    - Material relating to title-page
    - Proofs, notes on lay-out, prospectus
    - Paste-up
    - Material relating to prospectus (also forthcoming Paris Visit)
  - Duncan, Robert. A Paris Visit, 1985. Illustration by R.B. Kitaj. (85-229966) See also: Oversize: Broadsides, Small Broadsides, Folders, Large Folders (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, incl. Robert Duncan, 1983-86; Raymond Foye, 1981-84; R.B. Kitaj, 1984-85; Geoffrey Parton (Marlborough Fine Art), 1984-85; Stephen Stinehour (Meriden Gravure Co.), 1984; John Seliger, 1984
    - Published material relating to R.B. Kitaj
    - Typescripts
    - Paper samples, material relating to colophon, title-page
    - Material relating to illustration
    - Paste-ups
    - Proof
    - Dummy binding
  - Laughlin, James. The House of Light. 1986. Illustration by Vanessa Jackson. (87-141345) See also: Oversize: Broadsides (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, Vanessa Jackson, 1986, (4 items)
    - Miscellaneous notes and photocopies, invoice
    - Typescripts
    - Proofs, material relating to illustration
    - Paste-up
  - Laughlin, James.Tabellae, 1986. Illustration by Vanessa Jackson. (87-131523) See also: Oversize: Broadsides
    - Correspondence, James Laughlin, 1986-87, (36 items)
    - Correspondence, Vanessa Jackson, 1986, (5 items)
    - Typescripts, incl. a letter from James Laughlin, 1986, and items with annotations by Leslie Miller
    - Galleys
    - Material relating to lay-out
    - Material relating to illustration
    - Paste-up
    - Dummy copy (unsigned)
    - Promotional material, invoices
  - Cole. Peter. Rift, 1986. Illustration by Joel Shapiro. (87-176042) See also: Oversize: Broadsides (Box 14)
    - Correspondence, Peter Cole, 1986-87; Kamine, dated without year; Eli Gottlieb, 1986; Joel Shapiro, 1986; Michael, 1986
    - Typescripts
    - Proofs, paper samples, notes
    - Galleys
    - Paste-ups
    - Dummy bindings
    - Proof, samples of binding structure
    - Material relating to prospectus, publicity, incl. correspondence, John Ashbery, 1986; Harold Bloom, 1986; Cid Corman, 1986
    - Proof, samples of binding structure
  - Unbound sheets (Box 15)
  - Burroughs, William. The Cat Inside. 1986. Illustration by Brion Gysin. (87-205448) See also: Oversize: Broadsides, Folders, Large Folders
    - Correspondence, James Grauerholz (William Burroughs Communications), 1986 (2 items, incl. Memorandum of Agreement); Brion Gysin, 1986 (5 items); Andrew Wylie, 1985-86 (3 items); Mr. Mueller, 1986 (1 item); James, 1986 (1 item); Maria, undated (1 item); also material relating to Brion Gysin, William Burroughs
    - Typescripts
    - Photographs, work of Brion Gysin
    - Material relating to illustration
    - Proofs, notes, paper samples
    - Paste-up
    - Proof
    - Material relating to prospectus
  - Mathews, Harry. Singular Pleasures. 1988. Illustration by Francesco Clemente. (94-235051) See also: Oversize: Broadsides (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, Harry Mathews, 1988 (2 items); Michael Bixler, undated (1 item); Al Maschio, 1988 (1 item, with carbon)
    - Correspondence, Hiromi Katayama (Infusion, Ltd.), 1988; also invoice and advertisement, (10 items)
    - Typescripts
    - Notes on production
    - Paper samples, proofs, notes, material relating to illustration
    - Paste-up
    - Folded sheets (no printing)
    - Proofs
    - Material relating to promotion
  - Mathews, Harry. The Way Home, 1988. Illustration by Trevor Winkfield. (94-235074) See also: Oversize: Broadsides (Box 17)
    - Correspondence, Harry Matthews, 1987-88 (4 items); Robert Shapazian (Lapis Press), 1987-88 (5 items); Michael, 1987 (1 item); Claudia Cohen, 1988 (1 item); John Ashbery, 1988 (1 item); also material connected to prospectus
    - Typescripts
    - Notes, proofs, cloth sample, information relating to Trevor Winkfield
    - Proofs, paste-up, materials relating to illustration
    - Unbound sheets
  - Morrow, Bradford. A Bestiary, 1990. Illustration by Gregory Amenoff, Joe Andoe, James Brown, Vija Celmins, Louisa Chase, Eric Fischl, Jan Hashey, Michael Hurson, Mel Kendrick, James Nares, Ellen Phelan, Joel Shapiro, Kiki Smith, David Storey, Michelle Stuart, Richard Tuttle, Trevor Winkfield, Robin Winters. (92-107711) See also: Oversize: Broadsides, Folders
    - Correspondence, 1988-89, mostly to artists, invitations to participate
    - Notes relating to production
    - Typescripts
  - Laughlin, James. Angelica. See also: Oversize: Broadsides (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, Linda, 1992 (1 item); James Laughlin, 1992-93 (40 items); letterpress copy of poem (William Butler Yeats)
    - Typescripts
    - Photocopies of illustrations
    - Typescripts
    - Notes, proofs
    - Paste-ups, photocopies of paste-up
    - Proof
  - Howe, Susan. The Nonconformist's Memorial, 1992. Illustration by Robert Mangold. (93-228442) See also: Oversize: Broadsides (Box 19)
    - Correspondence, Susan Howe, 1990-93, (16 items)
    - Correspondence, Robert Mangold, 1991-92, (5 items)
    - Correspondence, Agnes Martin, 1991; also photostat relating to Agnes Martin, (1 item)
    - Typescripts, incl. one letter from Susan Howe, 1991
    - Notes
    - Biographical information relating to Susan Howe, Susan Mitchell DIA, Center for the Arts, Readings in Contemporary Poetry)
    - Paste-up
    - Proof
  - Kittredge, William and Robert Helm. Lost Cowboys. See also: Oversize: Broadsides
    - Correspondence, Kathryn Clark, 1992 (1 item); May Castleberry, 1992, (1 item)
    - Typescript, incl. one letter from William Kittredge to May Castleberry, 1991
    - Notes on production, proofs of publication information
    - Material relating to illustration, layout
    - Paste-up
  - Creelev, Robert. Life and Death. 1993. Illustration by Francesco Clemente. (95-222436) See also: Oversize: Broadsides.
    - Correspondence, Robert Creeley, 1993-94 (19 items); John Goodman, 1993 (3 items); Michael, [1993] (1 item); Peter Pettingill, [1993] (1 Item); Francesco Clemente, [1993] (1 item); Raymond [1993] (1 item)
    - Typescripts, proofs, notes.
    - Proofs, pasteup.
    - Proofs.
    - Material relating to illustration.
    - Paste-up.
    - "One Dummy", 24 plus cover"
    - Dummy.
    - Life and Death. Catalogue "published by Gagosian Gallery ... On the occasion of Francisco Clemente: The Black Paintings, 16 November 1993 to 8 January 1994."
- Miscellaneous Publications
  Publications designed by the Grenfell Press, including work for New Directions, Callaway Editions, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, Targ Editions, Conjunctions Magazine, etc.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein by title.
  - Calvino, Italo. The Silent Mr. Palomar. Targ Editions, 1981. (Box 20-23)
    - Unbound sheets Morrow, Bradford. Posthumes (Broadside poem). Santa Barbara: Cadmus Editions, 1982.
    - Typescript, notes, etc., incl. correspondence, Guy Davenport, 1982
  - Morrow, Bradford. The Preferences, 1983. (94-235066), (2 items)
    - Typescript
    - Proofs
    - Paste-up
  - Mailer, Norman. The Last Night. Targ Editions, 1984.
    - Galleys
  - Morrow, Bradford. After a Charme, 1984. (94-235070)
    - Typescript, proofs, notes
    - Paste-up
    - Unbound sheets
  - Michaux, Henri. Ideograms in China, 1984. (84-10006) See also: Oversize: Broadsides, Large Folders
    - Copies of correspondence, Peter Glassgold (New Directions) to Gustaf Sobin, 1984 (1 item); Peggy Fox to Henri Michaux, 1984 (1 item, with Gustaf Sobin to Henri Michaux, 1984, 1 item); Henri Michaux (?) to Gustaf Sobin, [1984?] (1 item); Gustaf Sobin to Henri Michaux, 1984 (1 item)
    - Typescripts, incl. copy of galleys
    - Material relating to publication information, notes, invoice, proofs
    - Material relating to binding and slipcase
    - Dummy binding
    - Unbound sheets
  - Targ, William. Abacus Now. Targ Editions, 1984. See also: Oversize: Broadsides (Box 21)
    - Typescripts
    - Paste-ups, notes relating to layout, incl. 1 letter from William Targ, 1989.
    - Material relating to illustrations
    - Proofs
    - Paper samples
    - Materials relating to Targ prospectuses The Grenfell Press 1985 Catalog, 1985.
    - Typescripts, paste-up, proofs
  - Morrow, Bradford. Kubler, Come Sunday. 1985. (94-235085)
    - Typescript
    - Paste-up
    - Proofs, galleys
  - Morrow, Bradford. More Ways Than One, 1985. (94-235091)
    - Paste-up.
  - Fisher, M.F.K. Spirits of the Valley. (86-131724) See also: Oversize: Broadsides
    - Typescript
    - Photocopy of corrected galleys, incl. one note from William Targ, 1985; photocopy of letter from M.F.K. Fisher, 1985
    - Miscellaneous material relating to production, incl. one letter from Sage Reynolds (Four Hands Design Studio), 1985; cost estimate, notes on layout, proofs, fabric sample, etc.
    - Paste-up
  - Greene, Graham. Reflections on Travels with my Aunt. 1989. See also: Oversize: Broadsides
    - Correspondence, Arnie Rougow, 1987-89, (4 items)
    - Typescript
    - Notes on production, layout
    - Paste-up
    - Proof
    - Text relating to prospectus
  - Rattray, David. Out of the Dark. 1989. (90-228872) See also: Oversize: Broadsides (Box 22)
    - Typescript, notes relating to colophon
    - Notes, sample of book structure, business card (Ted Cronin)
    - Proofs
    - Paste-ups
    - Finished book.
  - Oates, Joyce Carol. Heat, 1989. Illustration by Robert Gober. See also: Oversize: Broadsides
    - Typescripts
    - Notes relating to production, binding, etc.